Guide to the Genieve Lamson Papers, circa 1918-1944
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Genieve Lamson Papers
circa 1918-1944
Lamson, Genieve, 1887-1966
0.2 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The collection consists of notes taken by Genieve Lamson, Vassar College Professor of Geography 1922-1952, during her undergraduate studies at the University of Chicago. Also included are academic papers written by Vassar students attending Lamson's classes.
Biographical Note
Genieve Lamson was was born on April 27, 1887. She attended the University of Chicago, where she received her B.S. (1920) and her M.S. (1922). She also studied at Columbia University in New York City. She was on the faculty of Vassar College in the Geography Department from 1922 until her retirement in 1952. She retired to Randolph, Vermont, where she died on September 25, 1966.
Scope and Content Note
The Genieve Lamson Papers consist of notes taken by Lamson while she was a student at the Univeristy of Chicago in a class taught by Harlan H. Barrows called "Historical Geography of the United States." Also included are five academic papers written by Vassar students attending Lamson's classes.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
For additional biographical information, see the Vassar College Biographical Files Collection
Barrows, Harlan H., "Lectures on the Historical Geography of the United States as Given in 1933," edited by William A. Koelsch, University of Chicago, 1962.
Vassar College Student Materials Collection
Subject Headings
Names:
Barrows, Harlan H. (Harlan Harland), 1877-1960
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College--Students
Document Types:
Notes (documents); Papers (documents)
VCL Categories:
Vassar College
Encoding Information
Finding aid encoded by Jason Kovari, March 2009. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, June 2023.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Edward J. Miles, 1990.
Container List
- University of Chicago, "Historical Geography of the United States"
  - Reading list and notes, circa 1918 (Folder 1)
  - Lecture notes, p. 1-87, circa 1918 (Folder 2)
  - Lecture notes, p. 88-136, 145-155, circa 1918 (Folder 3)
  - Notes on 1800 census, circa 1918 (Folder 4)
- Vassar College Student Papers
  - Geography 370a: Bentley, Barbara, "Pioneer Expansion in New York State", 1933 Jan 19 (Folder 5)
  - Geography 372: Freeman, Anne B., "The Role Played by the Forests in the Settlement of the United States", 1944 Nov 20 (Folder 6)
  - [Geography 372?]: Gray, Matilda G., "The History of New Orleans and Its Importance in the Settlement of the Mississippi Valley", 1944 Nov 5 (Folder 7)
  - Geography 372a: Hutchins, Nancy, "Development of Transporation in the United States to the Railroad Era", circa 1944 (Folder 8)
  - Unknown Course: Strauss, Agnes, "Geographic Factors in American Railroad Development," notes, circa 1941 (Folder 9)